{"tossups": [{"question": "This pope illustrated the sun and moon allegory in which kings derive their power from the papacy. At the Fourth Lateran Council, this pope called a crusade that was defeated by the Ayyubid Sultan Al-Khalid; this man had earlier called a crusade that ended in the 1204 Sack of Constantinople. This pope feuded over Stephen Langdon\u2019s appointment as Archbishop of Canterbury with John I. The Albigensian Crusade persecuting the Cathars and the Fourth Crusade were both called by, for the point, what early 13th century pope who annulled the Magna Carta?", "answer": "Pope<b> Innocent III</b> (prompt on Innocent)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This policy is called the \u201cmost radical experiment\u201d in a book by Mei Fong, who claimed it was created by rocket scientists. Violators of their policy could lose their \u201ciron rice bowl,\u201d as they were blocked from holding government jobs. This policy, which was made less restrictive in 2016, has resulted in an increase in sex-selective abortion and a massive gender imbalance, due in part to a cultural bias in favor of having sons. For the point, name this policy meant to control the population of China.", "answer": "Chinese<b> one-child</b> policy (accept<b> Family Planning</b> Policy; accept<b> Dushengzi nu</b> zhengce; prompt on descriptions of population control before the end)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Referring to this location\u2019s one-time commander, William Delaplace, a commander allegedly said\u201cCome out you old rat!\u201d while seizing this location. Arthur St. Clair and Philip Schuyler [sky-ler] were accused of negligence for failing to defend this location. Louis-Joseph Montcalm defeated a frontal assault on this place during the Battle of Carillon. In 1775, this place was stormed by the Green Mountain Boys, led by Benedict Arnold and Ethan Allen. For the point, name this historic fort overlooking Lake Champlain.", "answer": "Fort<b> Ticonderoga</b> (accept Fort<b> Carillon</b> before Carillon is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this Italian physicist, the namesake of a national lab in Illinois.", "answer": "Enrico<b> Fermi</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After this battle, one man told the winner \u201cthe gods have not bestowed all things upon the same person,\u201d since the winner could not take advantage of this victory. This battle was fought near the Aufius River, which was used by the victors to trap the left flank of the losing side. Maharbal commanded the Numidian cavalry at this battle, while Gaius Terentius Varro co-led the Roman side. The victor of this battle had earlier won at Trebia and Lake Trasimene after crossing the Alps. For the point, name this 216 BC battle, a devastating loss for Rome that proved to be Hannibal\u2019s last major victory in Italy during the Second Punic War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Cannae</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This musician\u2019s partnership with Teddy Wilson produced hits like \u201cEasy Living\u201d and \u201cIf You Were Mine,\u201d and while with Brunswick Records, she released the popular song \u201cWhat a Little Moonlight Can Do.\u201d During a performance at the Cafe Society, she manipulated darkness to add to the emotional impact of a song originally written by Abel Meeropol; that song declares \u201cBlood on the leaves and blood at the root / Black bodies swinging in the Southern breeze.\u201d For the point, name this American jazz musician, nicknamed \u201cLady Day,\u201d who popularized the anti-lynching protest song \u201cStrange Fruit.\u201d", "answer": "Billie<b> Holiday</b> (or Eleanora<b> Fagan</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "One duke with this name waged the Mad War against his daughter Anne to preserve his kingdom, Brittany. A king with this name attracted controversy for his alliance with Suleiman the Magnificent and was defeated and captured at the Battle of Pavia. The king who met with Henry VIII at the Field of the Cloth of Gold had this name, as did the husband of Maria Theresa. An empire was dissolved after a leader with this name was soundly beaten at the Battle of Austerlitz. For the point, give this regnal name shared by the first Valois-Angoul\u02c6eme [val-wah ahn-goo-lem] king of France and the last Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b> Francis</b> (accept<b> Francis</b> II of Brittany; accept<b> Francis</b> I of France after \u201cSuleiman\u201d is read; accept<b> Francis</b> II after \u201cAusterlitz\u201d is read; accept<b> Fran\u00b8cois</b> or<b> Franz</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<em>Farmer v. Brennan</em> addressed the relevance of this constitutional amendment to sexual assault. The case of<em> Stack v. Boyle</em> concerned the application of this amendment to a group of suspected communists who were arrested under the Smith Act. The<em> Gregg</em> and<em> Furman</em> cases determined the standards of this amendment for Georgia laws concering people on Death Row. For the point, name this amendment that prohibits excessive bail, as well as \u201ccruel and unusual punishment.\u201d", "answer": "<b> 8</b>th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Oyama Isao was killed while trying to reach this city\u2019s Hongqiao [hong-chee-ow] Airport, which led to calls to dismantle the Peace Preservation Corps. This city was the site of the April 12 incident, in which the Kuomintang massacred thousands of Communist workers. An international settlement in this city, created by merging American and British enclaves, was essentially dissolved the day after the attack on Pearl Harbor. In the 1920s, four of China\u2019s largest banks were based in this city\u2019s Bund. For the point, name this metropolis on the Yangtze River, the largest city in China.", "answer": "<b> Shanghai</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A participant in one of these events claimed that the number of people killed in \u201cDemocrat wars\u201d in the 20th century could populate the city of Detroit. The line \u201cI knew Jack Kennedy. Jack Kennedy was a friend of mine. Senator, you\u2019re no Jack Kennedy\u201d was delivered by Lloyd Bentsen in one of these events in 1988. Paul Ryan\u2019s foreign policy was called \u201ca bunch of malarkey\u201d by Joe Biden in the 2012 iteration of, for the point, what political event that pitted Tim Kaine against Mike Pence on TV in 2016?", "answer": "<b> Vice President</b>ial<b> debate</b>s (prompt on debates; prompt on (political) campaign; do not accept or prompt on the phrase \u201cPresidential debate,\u201d but you can prompt on a generic description of a \u201cdebate during a presidential campaign\u201d if it\u2019s somehow clear the player isn\u2019t directly claiming the debaters are running for President themselves)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This Prime Minister investigated members of his party who were paid money on behalf of Mohamed al-Fayed to ask questions in Parliament for Harrods in the \u201cCash for Questions\u201d scandal. In the \u201cWar of Jennifer\u2019s Ear,\u201d Neil Kinnock attacked this leader with the slogan \u201cIf you want to vote Conservative, don\u2019t fall ill\u201d when criticizing long lines for healthcare. This leader\u2019s Downing Street Declaration in 1993 paved the way for the Good Friday Agreement signed by his successor. For the point, name this Conservative politician who succeeded Margaret Thatcher and preceded Tony Blair as Prime Minister.", "answer": "John<b> Major</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In 1992, state legislators tried to close the University of Oklahoma Law School because out-of-state donors funded a professorship in this woman\u2019s name. Joe Biden declined to call Angela Wright or any of three other witnesses to corroborate this woman\u2019s story. The phrase \u201chigh-tech lynching for uppity blacks\u201d was used to describe the proceedings in which this woman was brought before the Senate Judiciary Committee, where she detailed two years of sexual harassment by her boss. For the point, name this woman who testified in 1991 against Clarence Thomas during his Supreme Court nomination hearings.", "answer": "Anita<b> Hill</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The prelude to this man\u2019s abandoned opera<em> The Building of The Boat</em> was reworked into a piece in which the cor anglais represents a waterfowl in the realm of the dead. The finale of this composer\u2019s fifth symphony includes a horn motif inspired by swans taking flight. A tone poem by this man was performed under the title \u201cA Scandinavian Choral Hymn\u201d due to Russian censorship.The<em> Lemminkainen Suite</em> was composed by, for the point, what nationalist composer of \u201cThe Swan of Tuonela\u201d and<em> Finlandia</em>?", "answer": "Jean<b> Sibelius</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A ruler of this empire forced his Armenian citizens to march from Jugha to Isfahan, resulting in the creation of New Julfa. This empire retained control of Tabriz in the Peace of Amasya. The first ruler of this country became an alcoholic after losing the Battle of Chaldiran. Shamakhi was sacked by a group of rebels in response to Sultan Hasuyan\u2019s decision to convert this empire to Shia Islam. Ismail I founded, for the point, what early rival to the Ottoman Empire, an Iranian dyansty that collapsed in 1736?", "answer": "<b> Safavi</b>d dynasty (prompt on Persia; prompt on Iran before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A group of these people led a revolt that was put down by cavalry led by Patrick Gordon and Alexei Shein; that revolt sought to free Sophia Alekseyevna, and the brutal investigation into the revolt left over 1,000 of these people dead and hundreds more tortured. Regiments of these soldiers stormed the Kremlin in 1682 after a ten-year-old boy was named tsar. For the point, name this hereditary Russian military guard whose first units were created by Ivan the Terrible and which were mostly disbanded after a 1698 uprising against Peter the Great.", "answer": "<b> Streltsy</b> (prompt on generic answers like Russians, soliders, etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this event, Major General John Wool stated \u201cmartial law ought to be proclaimed, but I have not sufficient force to enforce it.\u201d An Irish mob destroyed the Colored Orphan Asylum as part of this event due to anger over blacks not being affected by the central issue. Henry Jarvis Raymond manned a Gatling gun to defend the<em> Times</em> building during this event, to which soldiers were re-routed fresh from a victory at Gettysburg. A $300 commutation fee helped spark, for the point, what 1863 riot over conscription?", "answer": "1863<b> New York</b> City<b> draft riot</b>s (accept<b> Draft Week</b>; \u201criot\u201d not needed after mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An artistic personification of one side of this war wears a blue coat and yellow sash and kneels on a stone crushing a hand. Another painting of this war shows a turban-wearing man riding a rearing horse as an old woman and nearly nude man lay in the foreground following the siege of the island of Chios [KAI-ohs]. The Romantic painter Eugene Delacroix [oo-zhen deh-lah-kwah] painted an allegory for this conflict in the ruins of Missolonghi. For the point, name this 19th century revolution against the Ottoman Empire by a Hellenic state.", "answer": "<b> Greek</b> War of<b> Independence</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> Greek Revolution</b>; only<b> Greek </b>is needed after \u201crevolution\u201d is read at the end)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The wonders of this city were chronicled by Ruy Gonzalez de Clavijo [cla-vee-ho], who was stationed there in the 15th century. A ruler who had just conquered this location got drunk in one of its palaces and killed his friend, Cleitus the Black. Ulugh Beg built an observatory in this city in the Transoxiana region, which was once a prominent capital of the Sogdians and a link on the Silk Road. In 329 BC, Alexander the Great conquered, for the point, what Central Asian city that was the capital of Tamerlane\u2019s empire?", "answer": "<b> Samarkand</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this city, James Bevel organized Project C, a plan for confrontation to attract media attention, culminating in a \u201cChildren\u2019s Crusade\u201d that met with resistance at Kelly Ingram Park. This city\u2019s police chief, Bull Connor, turned firehoses and German shepherds against child protesters in May 1963 during the SCLC\u2019s direct action campaign to integrate this city. Four months after that campaign, this city\u2019s 16th Street Baptist Church was bombed by white supremacists. For the point, name this Alabama city from whose jail Martin Luther King wrote a letter advocating nonviolence.", "answer": "<b> Birmingham</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Richard Delgado founded a school of legal thought named after the \u201ccritical\u201d study of this concept. Georges Cuvier used Sarah Baartman\u2019s irregular proportions to argue for his theory of this concept rooted in polygenism. Franz Boas\u2019s<em> The Mind of Primitive Man</em> attempted to disprove \u201cscientific\u201d theories of this phenomenon, which was controversially connected with intelligence by Hernstein and Murray\u2019s<em> The</em> <em>Bell Curve</em>. For the point, name this social construct that classifies human beings using physical traits, primarily skin color.", "answer": "<b> race</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "For two brief years, this building\u2019s Americana carillon was the largest in the world until its 538 bells were eclipsed in New York. For 11 days after the September 11 attacks, a skyward \u201cLegacy Light\u201d was lit on this building. After beating out Edward Carlson\u2019s giant balloon design with his \u201cgiant saucer\u201d plan, John Graham designed this building for the 1962 World\u2019s Fair. Mount Rainier and the Cascade Mountains are visible from the 520 foot high observation deck of, for the point, what tower, the tallest building in Seattle?", "answer": "<b> Space Needle</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this emperor who ruled Austria for over 60 years before dying in the midst of World War I.", "answer": "<b> Franz Joseph</b> I (accept<b> Francis Joseph</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "While in office, this politician suppressed the FREDEMO and APRA parties and attempted to arrest his predecessor, Alan Garcia. This man fell from prominence after videos showed his chief of intelligence, Vladimiro Montesinos, bribing election officials. This man was arrested for crimes against humanity for organizing the Grupo Colina death squad, which committed numerous atrocities while fighting the communist Shining Path insurgency. For the point, name this former president of Peru.", "answer": "Alberto<b> Fujimori</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man decreed that coffee could only be consumed by the royal family, a ruling he enforced by hiring disabled soldiers to sniff out illegal deposits. Johann Gotzkowsky was hired by this man to create a silk trade that could compete with rival France. This king commissioned Hans Knobelsdorff to design his summer palace in Potsdam, Sanssouci [sahn-soo-see]. This man argued that<em> The Prince</em> was a limited and biased work in his<em> Anti-Machiavel</em>, which was edited by his friend Voltaire. For the point, name this enlightened king who ruled Prussia for much of the 18th century.", "answer": "<b> Frederick II</b> (accept<b> Frederick the Great</b>; prompt on Frederick)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "J. Proctor Knott gave a satirical speech praising the \u201cUntold Delights\u201d of a city in this state. Part of the northern border of this state follows the Pigeon River and was established by the westernmost boundary proscriptions of the Webster-Ashburton Treaty. This state contains the Northwest Angle, a small area of land completely enclosed by Manitoba and the Lake of the Woods. Hubert Humphrey served as mayor of the largest city in, for the point, what state, home to Duluth and Minneapolis?", "answer": "<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An Islamist movement in this country was founded by the former math teacher Akrom Yoldoshev, and is thus popularly known as Akromia. Gulnara Karimova, the daughter of this country\u2019s former president, has been missing since her father\u2019s death; that president perpetrated the Andijan Massacre. Along with its northern neighbor, this country\u2019s irrigation for cotton farming is largely at fault for the shrinking of the Aral Sea. Islam Karimov once led, for the point, what Central Asian country with capital at Tashkent?", "answer": "<b> Uzbekistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In one work, this man advocated the payment of a one-time stipend to landless individuals after they reach the age of 21. James Chalmers wrote<em> Plain Truth</em> as a response to this man\u2019s most famous work. This man was tried<em> in absentia</em> for publishing a work that refuted Edmund Burke by arguing that the French Revolution was justified since it targeted the misdeeds of the institution of monarchy rather than the king himself. For the point, name this author of<em> Rights of Man</em> who proposed an American Magna Carta in his 1776 pamphlet,<em> Common Sense</em>.", "answer": "Thomas<b> Paine</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Barbara Hepworth\u2019s<em> Single Form</em> commemorates this man, whose spiritual struggles were laid out in haiku in the book<em> Markings</em>, derived from this man\u2019s journal after his death. Union Miniere may have ordered the death of this man while he was traveling to meet with Moise Tshombe in the midst of the Katanga Crisis. This man supervised the creation of a meditation room at UN headquarters after the resignation of Trygve Lie allowed him to assume his highest post. A plane crash killed, for the point, what Swedish UN Secretary-General known for his work in the Congo Crisis?", "answer": "Dag<b> Hammarskjold</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s force retreated across the Danube into Bessarabia to bait Ahmet Pasha into a trap at Slobozia, forcing the Ottoman Empire to sign the Treaty of Bucharest. This man replaced Barclay de Tolly in his most famous campaign, though the tsar had earlier overruled this man\u2019s apprehension in attacking a seemingly weak right flank at Austerlitz. This man conducted a successful scorched earth campaign during the French invasion of his homeland. For the point, name this Russian commander of troops at Borodino.", "answer": "Mikhail<b> Kutuzov</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Rather than inform her that he was arrested, this man told his mother that he got a job as assistant to the warden of the Montreal penitentiary. Before causing the failure of Hanover Trust, this man was able to buy a Lexington mansion and a locomobile off the profits of his most famous venture; that venture, replicated by men like Tom Petters and Bernie Madoff, involved a strategy described as \u201crobbing Peter to pay Paul.\u201d For the point, name this Italian businessman whose plan to pay off prior investors with the funds of new investors has become known as his namesake scheme.", "answer": "Charles<b> Ponzi</b> (or Carlo<b> Ponzi</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A February 6, 1958 disaster in this city was caused by James Thain\u2019s urgency to get a team back to England following a game against Red Star Belgrade; that disaster killed Duncan Edwards and other members of Manchester United. A 2005 Steven Spielberg film titled for this city depicts multiple failed assassination attempts against Ali Hassan Salameh by Mossad during Operation Wrath of God. For the point, name this city where 11 Israeli athletes were killed during the 1972 Olympics in Bavaria.", "answer": "<b> Munich</b> (accept<b> Munchen</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This event was the first time an American judge used the phrase \u201creasonable doubt,\u201d and possibly any judge worldwide. Two of the people convicted in this trial, Mathew Kilroy and Edward Montgomery, pled benefit of clergy and were branded on the thumb rather than be hanged. Robert Treat Paine led the prosecution team in this trial, which marked \u201cthe greatest service I ever rendered my country,\u201d according to defense attorney John Adams. Six British soldiers were acquitted in, for the point, what 1770 trial regarding the deaths of Crispus Attucks and four other colonists?", "answer": "<b> Boston Massacre</b> trial (accept descriptions of the trial, prosecution, acquittal, conviction, etc. of the perpetrators of the<b> Boston Massacre</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A porcelain statue of mute swans was gifted during this event, which included the issuing of a Joint Communiqu\u00b4e that promised normalization of relations. Photographs taken during an early part of this event were edited to crop out Winston Lord to avoid embarrassing Willam Rogers, the Secretary of State. This event, described as \u201cthe week that changed the world,\u201d was organized after a secret trip during an envoy to Pakistan by Henry Kissinger. Zhou Enlai helped plan, for the point, what 1972 event in which a sitting US president met with Mao Zedong?", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b>\u2019s visit to<b> China</b> (accept descriptive answers that mention both underlined parts; prompt on partial answers; prompt on descriptions of the first US Presidential visit to China)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "William Lovett used this movement to attack \u201cTaxes on Knowledge,\u201d and John Frost led members of it in the Newport Rising. The National Land Company was proposed by a leader of this movement, Feargus O\u2019Connor. The main document of this English movement called for equal representation of electoral districts and the secret ballot. This movement began after the 1832 Great Reform Act failed to grant non-land owners the vote. For the point, name this mid-1800s movement in England for increased voting rights, including universal male suffrage.", "answer": "<b> Chartism</b> (accept word forms, like<b> Chartist</b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A text sent by this group\u2019s namesake noted that \u201cHeaven has been determined to save your Country.\u201dIn response to learning about this group, one man said \u201cTo Sum up the whole, I have been a Slave to the service.\u201d This group\u2019s namesake was shot in a duel by John Cadwalader. Five years after this group\u2019s activities, John Armstrong advocated a similar goal in the Newburgh Conspiracy. Horatio Gates was supposed to replace a \u201cweak general\u201d in a plot by, for the point, what group that planned to oust George Washington as head of the Continental Army?", "answer": "<b> Conway</b> Cabal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This type of artwork influenced an artist who worked with Al Diaz in the group SAMO. The artist of<em> Horn Players</em>, Jean Michel-Basquiat, worked in this medium with an artist who painted Elizabeth II with David Bowie-like makeup. Examples of these artworks found in Pompeii include word squares and the words \u201cI made bread.\u201d A secretive artist created a girl letting go of a balloon, a work in this medium made with stencils and spray paint. For the point, name this type of art on public surfaces, created by artists like Banksy.", "answer": "<b> graffiti</b> (prompt on public art)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Prior to this battle, Wenceslaus IV attempted to calm tensions by arbitrating a dispute over Dobrin Land and Samogitia. Though the Treaty of Thorn was signed after this battle, hostilities broke out three years later in the Hunger War. During this battle, Ulrich von Jungingen was slain while fighting a coalition led by Jogaila and Vytautas, who had attacked Prussia. For the point, name this 1410 defeat of the Teutonic Knights that confirmed the rule of Poland-Lithuania over Eastern Europe.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Grunwald</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The National Protection War targeted this man due to his plan to reinstate the monarchy. In 1895, this man was given control of the Pacification Army and transformed it into the modernized New Armies. This man named himself the Hongxian Emperor, but his 1916 death ended his empire and ushered in the Warlord Era. This man negotiated an end to the Xinhai Revolution and the abdication of Puyi as the last Qing prime minister. For the point, name this Chinese general who, upon the resignation of interim president Sun Yat-Sen, became the first official leader of the Republic of China.", "answer": "<b> Yuan</b> Shikai (accept<b> Hongxian</b> Emperor before it is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A Herblock cartoon about this case shows James Glenn Beall passionately speaking as surrounding senators recoil in amazement.<em> Wallace v. Jaffree</em> and<em> Lee v. Weisman</em> expanded on the limit established by this case, whose majority opinion by Hugo Black noted that, although a text may be \u201cdenominationally neutral\u201d and its observance may be voluntary, it may still violate the Establishment Clause and/or the Free Exercise Clause. The phrase \u201cAlmighty God\u201d was present in a text struck down by, for the point, what 1962 Supreme Court case that banned school prayer in public schools?", "answer": "<b> Engel</b> v. Vitale", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Fran\u00b8cois Mansart renovated a building in this city that was given by Louis XIII to his brother as a wedding present. After the death of her husband, Marie de Medici was exiled to this city. A monarch born in this city signed the Treaty of Winchester to end a succession crisis caused by the drowning of the son of Henry I; that conflict between a man from this city and Matilda was called the Anarchy. For the point, name this French city near Orl\u00b4eans that was the birthplace of an English king named Stephen.", "answer": "<b> Blois</b> [blwah]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During Operation Crow, this man led guerilla fighters near Yogyakarta in the third of three defense areas called Wehrkreises. This man was given unlimited military authority to deal with the 1965 Tragedy, in which hundreds of thousands of communists and leftists were killed, via the Supersemar, a document that ultimately led to this man\u2019s rise to power. Economists called the Berkeley Mafia served this man, whose government was described as the New Order, which replaced Pancasila and Guided Democracy. For the point, name this president who replaced Sukarno to rule Indonesia.", "answer": "<b> Suharto</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A book of sayings attributed to this man has a name that translates as<em> Peak of Eloquence</em>. This man was pronounced a<em> Mawla</em>, or guardian, in a speech delivered near the pond of Khumm. This man, who wielded a legendary double-bladed sword named Zulfiqar, was assassinated by a Kharijite while praying in a mosque in Kufa. After the death of Uthman in 656, this man became the fourth caliph. For the point, name this cousin and son-in-law of Muhammad who is held to be the first Imam in Shia Islam.", "answer": "<b> Ali</b> ibn Abi Talib", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "After Republican victories in this state\u2019s 1872 elections, white Democrats attacked a courthouse and committed the Colfax Massacre; in the aftermath, the Supreme Court ruled in<em> U.S. v. Cruikshank</em> that federal charges could not be brought against the killers. A city in this state was subject to General Order No. 28, in which women who insulted Union soldiers were liable to be considered prostitutes and abused; that order was issued by Benjamin Butler, who occupied this state\u2019s largest city in 1862. For the point, name this state where the White League was founded in Grant Parish and committed racial violence in cities like New Orleans.", "answer": "<b> Louisiana</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Operation Cage hunted for suspects of a crime in this city; one perpetrator was eventually located in Subirats. This city was the site of a terrorist attack coordinated with one in Cambrils the same day; the prior day, stockpiled explosives destroyed a house in Alcanar, killing an imam who was believed to have plotted the attack in this city. For the point, name this city where over 100 people were injured in 2017 when a van crashed into pedestrians walking on the historic La Rambla in Catalonia.", "answer": "<b> Barcelona</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The \u201cMarch for the Presentation of Colors\u201d is usually omitted from a piece by this man originally written to celebrate an imaginary Napoleon victory. This composer called for three choirs in his Opus 22<em> Te Deum</em>, and he celebrated the tenth anniversary of the July Revolution with his<em> Grand Funeral</em> <em>and Triumphal Symphony</em> for wind band. \u201cReveries-Passions\u201d is the first movement of a piece by this composer that uses an<em> id\u00b4ee fixe</em> [ee-day FEEKS] and depicts a \u201cMarch to the Scaffold.\u201d For the point, name this French composer who dramatized his obsession with actress Harriet Smithson in the<em> Symphonie</em> <em>fantastique</em>.", "answer": "Hector<b> Berlioz</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 1916, this woman proposed a \u201cwinning plan\u201dthat incorporated accepting victories of partial suffrage at the state level as stepping stones toward a Constitutional amendment. A merger of Emma Smith DeVoe\u2019s NCWV and this woman\u2019s group formed the League of Women Voters. For the point, name this woman who succeeded Susan B. Anthony as President of the National American Woman Suffrage Association, or NAWSA.", "answer": "Carrie Chapman<b> Catt</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Displays at this event included a Javanese ensemble performing gamelan music and a \u201chuman village\u201d of African peoples. Buffalo Bill convinced Annie Oakley to join his Wild West Show during this event. The Eiffel Tower was built to serve as an entrance for, for the point, what 19th-century international exhibition held in Paris that featured, among other exhibits, a reconstructed Bastille to commemorate the hundredth anniversary of its storming?", "answer": "Paris<b> World\u2019s Fair 1889</b> (accept<b> Exposition Universelle</b> of<b> 1889</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "Inscriptions from this city include the Wagner murals, a series of fragments illegally removed by foreign visitors, and records of the king \u201cSpear-thrower Owl,\u201d who reigned for sixty years. The later Aztec god Quetzalcoatl may have evolved from a feathered serpent honored at this city\u2019s Ciudadela. The Avenue of the Dead is in, for the point, what eminent Mesoamerican city in the Valley of Mexico, the home of the Pyramids of the Sun and Moon?", "answer": "<b> Teotihuacan</b> ([tay-oh-tee-wah-kahn], but be lenient)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This politician co-sponsored a bill with Bella Abzug that would have provided $10 billion for child care services; that bill was neutered by Walter Mondale, and the small version was vetoed by President Nixon. A redistricting around Bedford-Stuvesant moved incumbent Edna Kelly\u2019s constituency and provided for this politician\u2019s first Congressional victory, in which she ran as \u201cUnbought and Unbossed.\u201dIn 1972, this politician became the first woman to seek the Democratic presidential nomination. For the point, name this New York politician, the first black congresswoman.", "answer": "Shirley<b> Chisholm</b> (accept Shirley Anita<b> St. Hill</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Gibson and Walk\u2019s \u201cvisual cliff\u201d experiment tested perception abilities among this group of people. Albert Bandura\u2019s social learning theory was developed at Stanford during the 1960s using this group of people as subjects. Piaget\u2019s four stages are used to categorize cognitive development in this group. Freud\u2019s oral, anal, phallic, and latent stages applied to this group, who supposedly experienced Oedipal urges. For the point, name this stage of human development.", "answer": "<b> child</b>ren (accept word forms and equivalents like<b> kid</b>s; accept<b> babies</b>,<b> toddler</b>s, and other equivalents; accept<b> boy</b>s and/or<b> girl</b>s)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s controversial seizing of nationalized property prior to leaving office became known as \u201cla pi\u02dcnata.\u201d This man\u2019s rule was challenged by loyalists of his former ally Eden Pastora and by the Miskito ethnic group, which formed the Misura rebel group. Over five months in 1980, this man\u2019s government reduced his country\u2019s illiteracy from 50% to 13%. This man won a Presidential election in 1984, but lost in 1990 to Violeta de Chamorro, who had been his colleague on a five-member panel set up in 1979 after the overthrow of the Somoza regime. For the point, name this leader of the Sandinista political movement and two-time President of Nicaragua.", "answer": "Daniel<b> Ortega</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This organization was targeted in Operation Sun-Apple, which had an initial budget of just $10,000. A member of this organization established 18 shell-companies in Panama to buy tax-free gasoline and offered Roy Cohn one million dollars to prevent his indictment. \u201cSonny Black\u201d had his hands cut off by this organization because he allowed the infiltration of Joseph Pistone. In 1985, this organization was decimated by the Commission Trial, which was made possible by the RICO act. The Five Families led, for the point, what organized crime outfit with Italian roots?", "answer": "the American<b> Mafia</b> (accept La<b> Cosa Nostra</b>; accept the<b> Mob</b>; do not accept the Sicilian Mafia)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An argument posed by this mathematician involves the construction of a sequence of binary numbers that fails to match any element of an infinite set of such sequences. This mathematician, who had a bitter rivalry with Leopold Kronecker and died in a sanatorium during World War I, discovered transfinite numbers and hypothesized there is no set with cardinality strictly between that of the integers and the reals. A \u201ctable\u201d with progressively removed planks is named for, for the point, what German mathematician who proved the reals are uncountable with a \u201cdiagonalization\u201d argument?", "answer": "Georg<b> Cantor</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "A minute of silence was observed before this piece was played at the Last Night of the Proms four days after 9/11, and this B-flat minor piece was played on-air during the announcements of FDR and JFK\u2019s deaths. For the point, name this slow, somber composition by Samuel Barber.", "answer": "<b> Adagio for Strings</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This event was sparked by the collapse of the National Cordage Company, which tried to corner the national hemp market. The failure of the Philadelphia and Reading Railroad also triggered this event, which was made worse by the combination of the McKinley Tariff and the Sherman Silver Purchase Act. J.P. Morgan authorized direct sales of gold to the US Treasury to help solve this event. Coxey\u2019s Army marched during, for the point, what economic panic that occurred during Grover Cleveland\u2019s second presidency, the worst of the 19th century?", "answer": "<b> Panic of 1893</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this war, a character is sent by Squire Woodcock to Paris with a secret message hidden in the false heel of his boot. Rab Silsbee dies in a skirmish during this war in a novel whose protagonist delivers the<em> Boston Observer</em> newspaper. This war provides the backdrop of a book in which a youth loses his hand in a silver smelting accident and befriends members of the Minute Men militia. For the point, name this war, the setting of Herman Melville\u2019s<em> Israel Potter</em> and Esther Forbes\u2019s<em> Johnny Tremain</em>.", "answer": "American<b> Revolutionary</b> War", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Josephus mentions a person named Amessis who was better known as this ruler. Our understanding of ancient quarrying techniques were revealed by the remains of the unfinished Obelisk II, commissioned by this ruler. This ruler\u2019s invasion of Punt brought back 31 myrrh trees and is celebrated at Deir-el-Bahri. This woman\u2019s stepson, Thutmose III, tried to remove references to her on monuments after her 1458 BC death. For the point, name this ruler, the longest-serving female pharaoh of Egypt.", "answer": "<b> Hatshepshut</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In this city, Alexander Dockery cancelled a bullfight, leading to the murder of Carleton Bass. A pair of wild dogs chased Len Tau for over a mile during a competition held in this city, which also hosted an event in which a Christiaan de Wet impersonator jumped into a pool twice a day as part of a massive reenactment of the Second Boer War. Legend holds that the waffle cone was invented in, for the point, what city that hosted the 1904 iteration of both the World\u2019s Fair and the Olympics, the largest city in Missouri?", "answer": "<b> St. Louis</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "At this location, an attack by Crow Indians prompted reports of \u201cfire and brimstone\u201d and led to the naming of the \u201cColter\u2019s Hell.\u201d This site was the subject of Ferdinand Hayden\u2019s Geological Survey of 1871, which concluded that this site should \u201cbe as free as the air or water\u201d and spurred an \u201cAct of Dedication,\u201din which Ulysses S. Grant made this site the first US National Park. For the point, name this national park that contains Old Faithful Geyser in Wyoming.", "answer": "<b> Yellowstone</b> National Park (accept<b> Colter\u2019s Hell</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Soviet Union\u2019s Arcos business in this country was raided in 1927 and found to contain secret cryptography rooms. In a 1933 show trial, six employees of an engineering firm from this country were arrested in Moscow and deported from the USSR. The Zinoviev Letter supposedly showed Soviet attempts to meddle in an election in this country. Soviet spies active in this country included Guy Burgess and Kim Philby. For the point, name this country where a Soviet spy ring was nicknamed the Cambridge Five.", "answer": "<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (accept Great<b> Britain</b>; accept <b>England</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of these people almost lost his job in 1805, partially because he had blindly accused a Wilmington printer of sedition. While serving in this job, Samuel Chase was impeached but acquitted by the Senate. In one of the last acts of his presidency - at metaphorical \u201cmidnight\u201d - John Adams appointed a large group of these people. The court case<em> Marbury v. Madison</em> concerned the appointment of, for the point, what government officials whose jobs are the concern of Article 3 of the Constitution and may serve on inferior and Supreme Courts?", "answer": "<b> judge</b>s (accept<b> justice</b>s; do not accept or prompt on lawyers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}